

Juan Ramos

+41 762 156 432 | ptjuanramos@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/juanramospt | Zürich, Schweiz

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Technical Lead with extensive experience, specializing in cloud migration and microservices architecture. Lead high-impact projects, achieving €1M in cost savings. Skilled in Azure solutions and strategic planning, with a strong focus on team collaboration and mentorship.

SKILLS

- Microsoft Certified: Azure
 Solutions Architect Expert
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Al Fundamentals
- .NET, Java, Python, ReactJS, Angular.
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Fundamentals
- Software architecture design
- Oracle SQL, SQL Server,
 PostgreSQL, Cosmos DB.
- Professional Scrum Master™ I (PSM I)
- Strategic planning design

EXPERIENCE

Technical Lead

Cognizant, 2024 - Current

- Lead a team of 20+ inshore and offshore on large-scale banking migration project at UBS.
- Successfully led two task forces to resolve project timeline issues.
 Collaborated with Solution Architects to migrate a monolithic fund reporting engine(handling over 30,000 daily reports) into a microservices architecture.
- Developed by using .NET, Python, Control-M, Autosys, Microservices, REST APIs, and Oracle SQL.
- **Engineered and deployed over 30 components** in OpenShift and on-premises, while beginning the design for Azure architecture.
- Responsible for ensuring adherence to UBS technical standards and infrastructure/compliance policies.
- Involved in project managing, assessing risks and multiple coordinating with program managers and ITILs.

Technical Architect

Unit4, 2021 - 2024

- **Architected and led 4 projects**, including HRMS and ERP systems, focusing on cloud data migration, multi-tenant applications and financial reporting functionalities.
- Designed and implemented a multi-tenant enterprise message broker, enabling real-time event distribution across decoupled HRMS and ERP microservices.
- Led a high-impact initiative to automate the migration of ERP client configurations from pre-production to production environments, ensuring data integrity, version control, and rollback capabilities.

- Led several architecture reviews and solutions to support cost saving of €1M over 2 years.
- Migrated on-premises solutions to Azure, leveraging SaaS, PaaS and laaS services.

Software Engineer

Agap2IT, 2018 - 2021

- Developed full-stack applications using Java, .NET, MySQL, and Azure, delivering tailored solutions across multiple sectors, including government and banking.
- Optimized a banking application, leading to a 25% increase in application performance.
- Achieved 100% sprint delivery, collaborating closely with stakeholders.
 Implemented applications using Docker and deployed on Azure environments (PaaS/laaS).
- Mentored junior developers and maintained code quality.

Software Engineer

Mater Dynamics, 2017 - 2018

- Mentored a small team of 5 elements, conducted code reviews, and aligned with strategic goals.
- Worked on pilot projects to **support pitches to clients and investors**, aiming to show the value and potential of our solutions.
- Developed and integrated REST APIs with front-end interfaces using Java, Spring, Codelgniter, jQuery, HTML/CSS3.
- Implemented mobile apps in Java with NFC scanning capabilities for logistics use.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science (B.S.): Computer Engineering

Faculdade de Ciências da Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon

LANGUAGE

| Portuguese | English | Spanish |
|-----------------|---------------|---------------|
| Proficient (C2) | Advanced (C1) | Advanced (C1) |

German

Intermediate (B1)